<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title></title>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2025-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Designing a universal e-reader grip</title>
        <published>2025-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-02-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/ereader-grip/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/ereader-grip/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/ereader-grip/">&lt;p&gt;I recently got a Kobo e-ink tablet to replace my Kindle. Amazon&#x27;s efforts to exert control over the Kindle devices &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.nytimes.com&#x2F;2009&#x2F;07&#x2F;18&#x2F;technology&#x2F;companies&#x2F;18amazon.html&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;wiki.rossmanngroup.com&#x2F;index.php?title=Amazon_Kindle_removes_download_feature_of_purchased_books&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; finally pushed me to drop the platform entirely. The device still works, and maybe I&#x27;ll jailbreak it to free it from Amazon&#x27;s control, but on principle I&#x27;m just giving up on it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Kobo reader is pretty identical in form-factor to the Kindle. Most e-ink readers are pretty similar in size, unless they&#x27;re doubling as a writing tablet, but at that point I don&#x27;t think of them as &quot;reader&quot; devices.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I have a couple e-reader devices, and they all suffer from the same problem: they&#x27;re designed to be slim and light and are incredibly uncomfortable to hold for long periods of time. They&#x27;re not really one handed devices. They&#x27;re &lt;em&gt;light&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; enough to be one-handed, but they&#x27;re too wide to be gripped&#x2F;held like a phone.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I was holding my new Kobo, my hand was cramping up and I thought about what would be better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted something more ergonomic. Something that would feel more like holding a tool. Maybe something like a game controller? Those are designed to be held for long stretches of time.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I searched around some 3D printing models and found a game controller grip designed for a phone. Not bad, I can probably modify the dimensions a bit to make it fit a tablet. After all, it&#x27;s just a bigger slab shape.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up with this:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;game-controller-grip.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;a kobo e-reader nestled in some playstation style controller grips on the lower half of the sides&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was pretty comfy, but suffered from a few drawbacks. It was too low on the device. My thumb could only just barely reach the touch screen&#x27;s lower corner quadrant without doing some awkward hand gymnastics. Also, the grips flare out, which means the weight distribution of the device is further away during one-handed use, making it feel heavier.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I needed to move the grips up the body of the tablet, and also reduce how flared the grips were.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I started thinking that maybe I could just print some ergo grips that just kinda clipped&#x2F;clamped on to the side of the device. There&#x27;s a little bit of a bezel on the outer edge of the reader, perhaps it could clip on to that without interfering with the screen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Many&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; failed iterations later, I realized that there just isn&#x27;t enough bezel to clip on to the side of the reader with enough strength. Look at all the little test clips I printed just to realize it was a bad idea:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;test-clips.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Side note: I did learn a lot about printing compliant mechanisms (clips with a bit of flex in them) though, so not entirely wasted effort.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I went back to the mental drawing board and thought about those spring loaded gamer grip things they have for phones. Y&#x27;know, like these things:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;8bitdo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;8Bitdo Ultimate Mobile Gaming Controller&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A slick idea, but now it would need to have moving parts and some sort of spring! No clue how I would pull that off. Also, it would be really great if as I was working through all these iterations if it was modular such that I didn&#x27;t have to reprint &lt;em&gt;the whole thing&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; when I just want to try out a new grip.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was gonna be a massive redesign.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I focused on the mechanical slider parts first, since that would require 2 interlocking parts, as well as some sort of spring action thing (?)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Printing 2 separate parts that fit together with very little wiggle room is actually pretty challenging. Kinda requires knowing your printer&#x27;s capabilities (which requires a lot of trial an error) and then adding or subtracting a fraction of a millimeter in various places. In my case it&#x27;s 0.2mm of space that I need to leave in order to make one part fit inside another part.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s also an additional consideration when 3D printing things, which is that they need to physically be printed out on a flat printer bed. You can&#x27;t print things in mid-air, so parts need to be designed to be built up layer-by-layer. The common workaround is printing &quot;supports&quot; alongside the desired object, with the intention of ripping them away afterwards. Somewhat like building scaffolding around a building during construction, and then removing it later. However, in practice, supports rarely come away from the print easily or cleanly, and you&#x27;re left with rough spots or a lot of &quot;post-processing&quot; work. In general, the less supports needed the better.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, back to the redesign... I got a bit of inspiration from &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;than.gs&#x2F;m&#x2F;21917&quot;&gt;this design&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which uses a typical office rubber band for the spring. Easy. Simple. Great!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made this combination of inner and outer slider parts, each with a little hook sticking out that the rubber band could wrap around. Then I added a rounded tab on the end of each of them, which I figured could act as the attachment point for whatever grips I came up with.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;side2.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;side1.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I printed a few quick test pieces, just to make sure the slider parts were dimensioned properly. No sense printing both full size parts only to find out they don&#x27;t fit together.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;test-parts1.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up printing a couple variants, but fortunately they fit pretty well. Snug enough to slide without being too loose and rattling. I also printed a test tab, just to give myself a sense of how the attachment would look&#x2F;feel.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, now I could confidently print the full size slider pieces. Unfortunately, the tab on the outer slider required printing supports, but there was no good orientation to print that piece that didn&#x27;t involve an overhang of some kind. Sacrifices had to be made. The surface left behind after removing the supports wasn&#x27;t too bad, and it&#x27;s gonna be hidden inside the grip handle anyway, so nobody will see it.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next up, I got to designing the handles. I measured the height and diameter of a screwdriver handle I thought was pretty comfortable and pretty much just did a cylinder with those dimensions. Nothing super complicated... except I also needed to put a groove in the handles to actually grip onto the tablet! 😅&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I needed to put slots in the handles for the tabs to slot into. And also some screw holes, to hold the whole thing together. So... maybe more complicated than I&#x27;d hoped, but this is still mostly a prototype.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s the handle I designed (and then just mirrored it for the other side)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;handles.png&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ll probably try to design something more fancy and ergonomic in a future revision, but for now, this worked out pretty damn well.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Behold! the final prototype!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;prototype1.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;prototype2.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;prototype3.jpg&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had to double-loop the rubber band for a stronger grip action, but I&#x27;m quite pleased with how well this worked out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#x27;s kinda amazing how holding a thing in your hands immediately gives you new ideas. Future revision ideas:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ergonomic handles. These are fine, but some more curves and something to hook a finger into would be good.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The grooves for holding the tablet should maybe be part of the sliders, rather than part of the handles? That might free up the handle design from having to incorporate grooves for the tablet.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe figure out a way to attach the sliders to the handles without needing screws at all. There&#x27;s some clever &quot;clip&quot; mechanisms I could try to incorporate.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, if you made it this far, thanks for reading!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Rapid Prototyping with 3D printing</title>
        <published>2025-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/rapid-prototyping/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/rapid-prototyping/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/rapid-prototyping/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Author&#x27;s Note:&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Many folks reading this may not know or care about 3D printing, so I&#x27;ll try to keep the technical jargon to a minimum.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve been working on improving my CAD skills lately. I&#x27;ve had a 3D printer for a few years now, but for much of that time I mostly would just download other people&#x27;s 3D models from various sites and print them. My ability to &lt;em&gt;imagine&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; a thing in my mind and then just make it into a physical thing was quite limited by my inability to use &lt;em&gt;real&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; CAD software.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mostly used &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;tinkercad.com&quot;&gt;TinkerCAD&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for very simple designs. I could make a box. I could make a cylinder. I could make a sphere. I could combine those things in various ways, but it never really resulted in &lt;em&gt;slick&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; looking designs, just minimally functional.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m now getting much better at using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;onshape.com&quot;&gt;Onshape&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; which is way more full featured, but also a way steeper learning curve.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now is the time when I give a shout-out to Michael Laws for his Youtube series &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.youtube.com&#x2F;playlist?list=PLGqRUdq5ULsONnjEEPeBxxStEsobDKAtV&quot;&gt;3D Design for 3D Printing&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Hugely helpful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the increased complexity of designs I&#x27;m able to accomplish, I&#x27;m learning the importance of &quot;will this little mechanical part work?&quot; -- hinges, screw holes, interlocking parts, and all the other exacting aspects of a functional thingie often require a cycle of printing the thing, testing it, and adjusting the model again. 3D models on a computer are very exact, but the strand of hot plastic goo that comes out of a 3D printer is nowhere near as exact.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cycle of design -&amp;gt; print -&amp;gt; adjust design -&amp;gt; print can be quite time consuming. 3D prints can take many hours to complete depending on size, and it is quite frustrating to wait many hours for something to print only to find out that the measurements in your computer model don&#x27;t work once they&#x27;re printed in the really real world.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately, there&#x27;s a trick one can do to make the adjust + printing cycle much faster. As an example, I&#x27;ll use a project I&#x27;m working on right now, which involves a part that slides into a groove on another part, and a screw that will lock the slider in place.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;skullvalanche.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;rapid-prototyping&#x2F;model.png&quot; alt=&quot;3D Model&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I need to make sure the screw and the screw hole work well together. I also need to make sure the slider slab fits in the groove cut-out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When 3D printing stuff, you load your 3D model into an app called a &quot;slicer&quot; which plots out the path that the printer will follow as it builds up your print out of many very thin layers (slices).&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#x27;s an example of what that looks like:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;skullvalanche.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;rapid-prototyping&#x2F;full-slice.png&quot; alt=&quot;fully sliced= model&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice down in the corner it estimates that printing this stuff will take 67 minutes to print.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;BUT, this is a slicer application! In addition to &quot;slicing&quot; your model into many horizontal layers, The slicer can also make arbitrary cuts in your model, allowing you to discard the parts that don&#x27;t need testing. You can just print the portion of your model that needs testing!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, in this case, we can just print a tiny portion of the full model which will allow me to check the screw + hole + groove without needing to print the full thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the image below, it&#x27;s just a little chunk of the full model, but it has all the important parts that need test-fitting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;skullvalanche.com&#x2F;blog&#x2F;rapid-prototyping&#x2F;test-slice.png&quot; alt=&quot;partial model slice&quot; &#x2F;&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also if we look down in the corner, the estimated print time is down to 25 minutes from the 67 minutes in the full print. If it works, great, then we can print the full size model with confidence. If it doesn&#x27;t work, at least we saved time (and materials) by only printing a tiny little chunk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I kinda assume someday 3D printers will be cheap enough and good enough that they become a common household appliance, much like paper printers were after the 90s. Not everyone will be a 3D CAD modeller, of course, but being able to download a file and print out a part for &lt;em&gt;stuff&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is extremely handy.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hooray for the future.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On a more technical note for the 3D modelers out there: I find that shrinking the bolt diameter by .25mm and also expanding the screw hole diameter by .25mm from the theoretical in a 3D model tends to result in a perfect fit. 😁&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Zola&#x27;s ball</title>
        <published>2025-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-14T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/zola/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/zola/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/zola/">&lt;p&gt;Warning: while I will do my best not to make too many assumptions about the tech savviness of my readers, this is a deep dive into the tech I use to run this blog.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Someone asked what technologies I&#x27;m using to host this blog. While I have a background in web development about 20 years ago, I&#x27;m extremely rusty in almost all ways that matter. I also know enough to know that the modern web is a hellscape of javascript frameworks, typescript pre-processors, and Beelzebub knows what else. This is a goddamn blog. It&#x27;s text and images. This shit could run on a calculator. I don&#x27;t want to have to think too hard about adding new text and images.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;d rather not have to monkey with writing HTML code just to post a new entry, and I&#x27;m reasonably familiar with &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.markdownguide.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Markdown&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;, so a &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Static_site_generator&quot;&gt;static site generator&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; just made the most sense.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;TLDR for the people who&#x27;s eyes are already glazing over: I write some plain text markdown files, and then I run an app called &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;getzola.org&quot;&gt;Zola&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; that turns those text files into HTML files I can upload to a web server.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-zola&quot;&gt;Why Zola?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; of SSGs out there, but most of them are written in Node or Python or other languages which have a tendency to either mess with your system&#x27;s environment, or I would need to install the SSG in a virtual environment. Both of those options sound like extra headache I do not want to have to think about.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Zola is a single binary executable. Everything it needs in order to run is baked into a single file. No mess, no fuss.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-zola&quot;&gt;Using Zola&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Warning: There is no GUI for Zola.&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are looking for a drag-and-drop solution with pretty buttons and such, Zola is not that. If you are familiar with command-line stuff, setting up Zola will be fairly straightforward. Command-line skills are well beyond the scope of this blog post. 😅&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The rest of this post assumes some familiarity with the particulars of web hosting, HTML, CSS, Javascript, and command-line tools.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.getzola.org&#x2F;documentation&#x2F;getting-started&#x2F;overview&#x2F;#first-steps-with-zola&quot;&gt;This page&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; pretty well walks you through how to get started with Zola.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m not gonna reinvent their documentation. Instead I&#x27;m gonna mostly focus on the things that tripped me up initially.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the root of your freshly initialized site folder there&#x27;s a &lt;code&gt;config.toml&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; file. This is where your customized settings live.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I added the line &lt;code&gt;generate_feeds = true&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; so I could have an Atom RSS feed. This is a blog after all, people should be able to subscribe to it. Other than that, mostly I just disabled features which I knew I wouldn&#x27;t need, and modified some file paths since the blog is a sub-section of skullvalanche.com, rather than the full thing. You can see my full config file &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;skullvalanche&#x2F;skullvalanche.github.io&#x2F;blob&#x2F;main&#x2F;blog-src&#x2F;config.toml&quot;&gt;here&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other things that proved to be non-obvious involved where to put files when writing blog posts.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Zola docs walked me through setting up template files, and that was all fine, but I wanted to put a javascript file somewhere. I also wanted to put a CSS file somewhere. Where do those go? How do I reference them?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s a folder named &lt;code&gt;static&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; which is for - you guessed it - static asset files. Things which aren&#x27;t markdown to be rendered, but still need to exist for your HTML output files to work. I went with &lt;code&gt;static&#x2F;style.css&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and my js file in &lt;code&gt;static&#x2F;js&#x2F;minimal-theme-switcher.js&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; -- then to reference these files in my in my templates I had to use &lt;code&gt;{{ get_url(path=&#x27;style.css&#x27;) }}&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;{{ get_url(path=&#x27;js&#x2F;minimal-theme-switcher.js&#x27;) }}&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; respectively. The templating language is clearly very powerful, but I haven&#x27;t done a deep dive into using it yet. The docs are well written. Watch out for Rickrolls.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Text only blog posts can just be markdown files in the root of content. e.g. &lt;code&gt;content&#x2F;2025-01-13.md&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blog posts which have &quot;accompanying&quot; files, like images, need to be in folders along with their files. Also the file should be named &lt;code&gt;index.md&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;e.g.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;content&amp;#x2F;2025-01-13&amp;#x2F;index.md
content&amp;#x2F;2025-01-13&amp;#x2F;image1.jpg
content&amp;#x2F;2025-01-13&amp;#x2F;image2.jpg
&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly, just clicking around my &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;skullvalanche&#x2F;skullvalanche.github.io&#x2F;tree&#x2F;main&#x2F;blog-src&quot;&gt;blog-src&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; folder will probably give a decent concept of how things are structured.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you&#x27;re ready to turn your markdown into HTML, &lt;code&gt;zola build&lt;&#x2F;code&gt; will quickly generate your output files into the folder specified in your config. That&#x27;s about it. You can upload the resulting output to whatever hosting solution you wish.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;github-pages&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other part of this blog&#x27;s tech stack is &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;pages.github.com&quot;&gt;Github Pages&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#x27;s not really much to say about GH Pages that isn&#x27;t already in the linked docs above. I just figured if I&#x27;m gonna use a very code centric approach to having a blog, might as well just host it (for free) from Github.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;comments-via-giscus&quot;&gt;Comments via giscus&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To enable comments on your blog, you can integrate Giscus, a comments widget that uses GitHub Discussions. See &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;giscus.app&quot;&gt;giscus.app&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; for how to set it up.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-ramblings&quot;&gt;Final ramblings&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this is somewhat helpful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;P.S. bonus heart container if you get the reference in the title.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Thanks Stevie</title>
        <published>2025-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-13T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/stevie/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/stevie/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/stevie/">&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t like Fleetwood Mac. I don&#x27;t think I&#x27;ve ever purposefully played a Fleetwood Mac song, except to maybe win an argument or something. I do, however, like Stevie Nicks&#x27; voice. I did a deep dive on Stevie&#x27;s solo catalog a while back to verify something though.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&#x27;t like Stevie Nicks&#x27; music.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This presents a weird situation in which I enjoy many artists who are clearly &lt;em&gt;influenced&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; by Stevie Nicks, but don&#x27;t like the source material. I even have a list of artists who I categorize as influenced by her, but make different (better?) musical choices.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Only 2 exceptions leap to mind:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stop Draggin&#x27; My Heart Around (with Tom Petty)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stand Back&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably because both those songs don&#x27;t feel like her typical stuff.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wish she&#x27;d do more collabs with artists who&#x27;s musical styles I like. Though, at 76 years old, I think time may be running short for that to happen.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I keep a list of artists who I think owe a debt of gratitude to Stevie, and that&#x27;ll hafta tide me over.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.hopesandoval.com&#x2F;music&#x2F;index.shtml&quot;&gt;Hope Sandoval&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; (Mazzy Star vocalist)&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;music.youtube.com&#x2F;channel&#x2F;UCZcsJ45sZWzUeLJUaoJzv9g&quot;&gt;Speck Mountain&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;music.youtube.com&#x2F;channel&#x2F;UCNvXQkhLIXu_DAoHtmRURFA&quot;&gt;Widowspeak&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;music.youtube.com&#x2F;channel&#x2F;UC80gbN8WYkFPjSvU2wK7Kxg&quot;&gt;Haley Bonar&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;music.youtube.com&#x2F;channel&#x2F;UCbLt7pataRom2AHyWfBFuVQ&quot;&gt;Still Corners&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;music.youtube.com&#x2F;channel&#x2F;UCMI6aRzQDJ1a6A4asjQKbYg&quot;&gt;Tess Parks&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>SRSLY Youtube Music, WTF</title>
        <published>2025-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/wtf-ytm/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/wtf-ytm/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/wtf-ytm/">&lt;p&gt;Things to know ahead of time: I listen to a lot of &quot;off the beaten path&quot; music genres. I also spend a lot of time looking for &lt;em&gt;new&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; music. I am reasonably certain this is reflected in my YTM library&#x2F;playlists&#x2F;usage patterns. All of which are things I would expect Youtube engineers to factor into their product.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I rant about how bad the Youtube Music &quot;suggestions&quot; algorithm is frequently. I hate it, and yet I keep using YT Music in spite of everything.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At some point I need to just realize the blame is mine. This is me failing to just go use a different platform. But first, I will take this opportunity to rant yet again about how bad their suggestion algo is. Never let a complaint opportunity go to waste.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#x27;s examine some evidence. Here&#x27;s a lovely screenshot of the algo taking a playlist consisting (mostly) of Post-Punk, Post Rock, and Shoegaze artists... what do they suggest I add?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;wtf1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;a playlist consisting of a bunch of post-punk songs, followed by the suggestion to add Drake and Olivia Rodrigo to the playlist&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The top suggestion? More Cold Cave. Okay, that&#x27;s a bit on-the-nose, but considering the playlist has an entire Cold Cave album in it, sure.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next suggestion is equally on-the-nose, since there is also Kasabian in the playlist. Okay fine.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then &lt;strong&gt;Olivia Rodrigo&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; ? Go home, YTM, you&#x27;re drunk.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The suggestions algo seems to throw up its hands after 2 simplistic suggestions and just default to &quot;well, these songs are popular, generally speaking&quot;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I would expect more from a company that is literally trying to lead the way on putting AI in every damn thing.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, let&#x27;s try something else. I&#x27;ll queue up 1 relatively obscure song by the Belarussian band Molchat Doma and see what the autoplay queues up for me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;wtf2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;a playlist which rapidly steers towards the the most popular songs of the genre&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot;&#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twin Tribes? ULTRA SUNN? okay, so far so good...&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the Silence? ENJOY THE GODDAMN SILENCE? You think I put in Molchat fucking Doma only to be steered to a song that spent 3 weeks in the Top 10? 🤦‍♂️&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hmm, maybe it was just a one-off... oh, nope, The Cure. Of course. Another Top 40 hit by a band pretty much everyone and their mom has heard of.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, if I&#x27;m being generous, the &lt;em&gt;only&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; explanation for this kind of suggestion algorithm is if it&#x27;s built around the idea &quot;oh, maybe you might like some of the bands which were influences on the band you&#x27;re currently listening to&quot;. I would expect better from a Google product though. Surely they have enough behavior data on me to know better than that.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Do better, Youtube Music.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Mastodon Matters</title>
        <published>2025-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/mastodon-matters/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/mastodon-matters/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/mastodon-matters/">&lt;p&gt;Apologies if this looks like a huge wall of text at first glance. Please stick with me.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Really the title of this should be &quot;The Fediverse Matters&quot; but the word &quot;Fediverse&quot; is not widely recognized, and &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;joinmastodon.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;Mastodon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; is basically the dominant platform within the Fediverse, so ... here we are. Pedantry will get me nowhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Social media, whether we like it or not, plays a significant role in shaping modern society.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The history of social media thusfar has proven to me that any platform operated for profit is doomed to suffer &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;Enshittification&quot;&gt;enshittification&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;. Sooner or later shareholders demand that the line goes up 📈 and principles fall to the way-side.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But social media is now an integral part of modern life! Giant companies and organizations with massive influence over daily life leverage these platforms to sway public opinion constantly. Policy discussions happen on these platforms. &lt;em&gt;Governments&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; use these platforms to communicate to their citizens.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet these platforms are owned and operated by private for profit entities? What A Terrible Idea™!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what does that leave us? &lt;em&gt;Protocols&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; rather than platforms.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twitter, Facebook, Tiktok, etc... those are &lt;em&gt;platforms&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. They do not inter-operate with each other. They want to lock you in on their platform to get your precious ad revenue generating attention.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Email, on the other hand, is a &lt;em&gt;protocol&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; -- you can send email from Gmail to Outlook or Yahoo or Proton or whatever. They all speak the same SMTP protocol. Protocols enable inter-operability.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fediverse is built on top of the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;en.wikipedia.org&#x2F;wiki&#x2F;ActivityPub&quot;&gt;ActivityPub&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;em&gt;protocol&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; -- it means it can easily interoperate with any other server which also speaks ActivityPub.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Part of the &quot;problem&quot; with platforms is the network effect -- the more people are on that platform, the harder it is to leave it, cuz all your connections are there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, think about Facebook. Lots of people at this point hate Facebook. Why is anyone still there? Because their connections are still there. Network effect. If you leave FB you may lose all those personal connections that only happen via FB.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if you could take your network with you? That&#x27;s exactly what ActivityPub allows for. There&#x27;s a lot of platforms that work with ActivityPub: Mastodon, Lemmy, Pleroma, Pixelfed, etc - but they all can talk to eachother, so if you wanna use Pixelfed, but your buddy wants to use Mastodon... that&#x27;s fine! You can still at least see eachother&#x27;s content. And if you wanna switch from Pixelfed to Pleroma... that&#x27;s fine too, you can take your contact list with you and up n&#x27; move. Your buddy on Mastodon can stay there.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, but how does this solve the broader ailments of society?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because it allows for anyone to run their own social media platform, but still reach a global audience. The German government can run their own social media platform, hand out accounts to every government employee, and those gov employees can still have their social media posts received by people using a completely different platform run by a socialist collective in Peru. Protocols enable inter-operability and inter-operability avoids platform lock-in.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you don&#x27;t like the way your platform administrator is running things... you can hop to a different platform or even set up your own. All without worrying about having to &quot;start over&quot; rebuilding your connections. Network effect is mitigated.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also means you can seek out a platform which isn&#x27;t run by a sociopath billionaire. If your Fediverse server admin suddenly starts running things in new and distasteful ways... you are free to take your social network presence elsewhere.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The irony of this rant is that I&#x27;m advocating for leaving those locked-in social network connections which you can&#x27;t take with you... but in theory this is a one-time concern. Once you&#x27;re the owner of your social network, that&#x27;s it, it&#x27;s yours from that point forward.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hopefully this convinces at least some folks to make the leap 🤞 - I will make a follow-up post about navigating the nuances of actually joining the Fediverse.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Fake Lego</title>
        <published>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/fake-lego/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/fake-lego/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/fake-lego/">&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve had this Shai Hulud &lt;strike&gt;Lego&lt;&#x2F;strike&gt; brick kit on my wishlist for a long time, and this past holiday someone finally got it for me. Yay!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;shai-hulud-not-lego.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fake Lego set of Shai Hulud&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The exercise of putting it together has reminded me why Lego™ is the leader in this domain. The fit and polish of this kit is not quite right. Some pieces are clearly of the &quot;Lego would never do that&quot; camp. In particular this kit relies a lot on tiny little nub pieces that allow you to connect the &quot;back&quot; of 2 bricks to eachother. It&#x27;s a clever hack, but it&#x27;s &lt;em&gt;so damn fiddly&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; that I can understand why lego never implemented such a mechanic.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also this kit uses some rubber connectors to give the worm flexibility-- which, again, is a clever hack, but Lego would never do that. There&#x27;d be some clever pivoting stuff instead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I guess I&#x27;m a Lego snob.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Gotta start somewhere</title>
        <published>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2025-01-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Skullvalanche
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/gotta-start-somewhere/"/>
        <id>https://skullvalanche.com/blog/gotta-start-somewhere/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://skullvalanche.com/blog/gotta-start-somewhere/">&lt;p&gt;Occasionally I have an itch to write things which are probably best captured in a semi-permanent, semi-long form medium. &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;gladtech.social&#x2F;@skullvalanche&quot;&gt;Mastodon&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; posts are artificially short and (at least in my case) ephemeral on purpose.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I guess I&#x27;ll see how well this blog works out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m currently using &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;getzola.org&quot;&gt;Zola&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; to generate the static files. I&#x27;m a total n00b to Zola, so this will likely start out looking quite minimal and maybe build up to be fancier over time? Or not! I&#x27;m a big fan of form-follows-function. What could be more functional than text on a page?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;m a bit disappointed that Zola doesn&#x27;t have better &quot;sensible defaults&quot; as far as output, but perhaps I&#x27;m just not using it in the same way that the software developer envisioned.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The more my software development journey progresses, the more I recognize that it&#x27;s very easy to create a tool and think &quot;surely it&#x27;s obvious how to use this&quot; only to have someone immediately use it in an unexpected way and result in horrible bugs. Be empathetic with software developers.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wonder how I add a &quot;back&quot; link on these pages? Surely I can figure that out.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ah, yes, this will do:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
